<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OpenChain KWG – Appendix</title><link>https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/</link><description>Recent content in Appendix on OpenChain KWG</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Guide: 1. Open Source Policy (Sample)</title><link>https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/1-policy-template/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/1-policy-template/</guid><description>
&lt;div class="alert alert-primary" role="alert">
&lt;h4 class="alert-heading">Note:&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>This sample open source policy was written with reference to the following two materials.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenChain-Project/Reference-Material/blob/master/Open-Source-Policy/Official/2.1/en/Open-Source-Policy-Template-en-OpenChain2.1-ISO5230.xlsx">OpenChain Open Source Policy Template&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/todogroup/policies/blob/master/linuxfoundation/lf_compliance_generic_policy.pdf">Linux Foundation Generic FOSS Policy&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="1-purpose">1. Purpose&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="1-purpose-of-the-policysub3131sub">(1) Purpose of the policy&lt;sub>(3.1.3.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This policy provides the following principles for all organizations involved in software development, service, and distribution in [COMPANY] (hereinafter referred to as the &amp;ldquo;Company&amp;rdquo;) to properly utilize open source software (hereinafter referred to as &amp;ldquo;Open Source&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Principles for open source license compliance&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Principles for contribution to external open source projects&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Principles for releasing open source&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>These principles provide a way for all members of the company to understand the value of open source, use it correctly, and contribute to the open source community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All members of the company can view the open source policy at the following link on the in-house wiki: [internal_link]&lt;sub>(3.1.1.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-impact-of-non-compliance">(2) Impact of non-compliance&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It is important that [COMPANY] adheres to this policy. Failure to do so may lead to:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>legal claims from the holders of copyright or other intellectual property rights in code we use&lt;/li>
&lt;li>claims from our customers;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the inadvertent release of [COMPANY] proprietary code;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>breach of regulatory obligations by [COMPANY] potentially leading to fines;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>loss of reputation;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>loss of revenue;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>breach of contract with suppliers and customers.
For this reason, we take breaches of this policy seriously, and any individual breaching the policy may find themselves subject to [COMPANY]&amp;rsquo;s disciplinary procedure.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="3-how-to-contribute-to-the-effectiveness-of-the-program">(3) How to contribute to the effectiveness of the Program&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>All members of the company can contribute to the effectiveness of the program and improvement of the company&amp;rsquo;s compliance level by understanding the rationale and content of this policy and faithfully performing the necessary activities.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="2-scopesub3141sub">2. Scope&lt;sub>(3.1.4.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This policy applies to the following three parts:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Applies to [all products provided or distributed by the company externally]. However, the open source only for internal use is not included in the scope of this policy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Applied when contributing to external open source projects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Applied when releasing internal code as open source.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The scope can be changed according to the business environment of the company, and the procedure for this is as follows.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>If the open source program manager determines that it is necessary to change the scope of policy according to changes in the company&amp;rsquo;s business environment, such as a new business or reorganization, submit a proposal for this to the OSRB.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>OSRB approves proposals for scope changes at the appropriate level.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>OSRB modifies the open source policy to change the scope of the policy.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="3-terms">3. Terms&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;compliance artifacts&amp;rdquo; - a collection of artifacts that represent the output of a compliance program and accompany the supplied software. The collection may include (but is not limited to) one or more of the following: attribution notices, source code, build and install scripts, copy of licenses, copyright notices, modification notifications, written offers, open source component bill of materials, and SPDX documents.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;open source&amp;rdquo; - software subject to one or more licenses that meet the Open Source Definition published by the Open Source Initiative (see opensource.org/osd) or the Free Software Definition published by the Free Software Foundation (see gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html) or similar license.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;program&amp;rdquo; - the set of policies, processes and personnel that comprise an organization’s open source license compliance activities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;program participants&amp;rdquo; - any organization employee or contractor that defines, contributes to or has responsibility for preparing supplied software. Depending on the organization, that may include (but is not limited to) software developers, release engineers, quality engineers, product marketing and product management.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>“SPDX” - the format standard created by the Linux Foundation’s SPDX (Software Package Data Exchange) Working Group for exchanging bill of materials for a given software package, including associated license and copyright information (see spdx.org).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;supplied software&amp;rdquo; - software that an organization distributes to third parties (e.g., other organizations or individuals).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="4-roles-responsibilities-and-competenciessub3121sub">4. Roles, Responsibilities and Competencies&lt;sub>(3.1.2.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In order to ensure the effectiveness of the policy, the roles and responsibilities and the competencies that the person in charge of each role should have are defined as follows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The person/group in charge of each role and the required competency level are defined in [Appendix 1. Status of Person in Charge].&lt;sub>(3.1.2.2)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The open source program manager periodically updates the list according to the company&amp;rsquo;s business situation.&lt;sub>(3.2.2.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The head of the organization responsible for each role designates a person in charge within the organization, and allocates appropriate time and budget for the person in charge to fulfill the role.&lt;sub>(3.2.2.2)&lt;/sub>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The person in charge of each role should raise an issue with the open source program manager if appropriate support is not provided while performing his/her role.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The open source program manager discusses problem solving with the head of the organization. If not properly resolved, the open source program manager may request the OSRB to resolve the issue.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>OSRB shares the problem with the head of the higher level organization and asks for a solution.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="1-osrb">(1) OSRB&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>OSRB&lt;sub>Open Source Review Board&lt;/sub> is a consultative body composed of an open source program manager, legal team, patent team, development team, and infrastructure team for the company&amp;rsquo;s open source compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Create policies and processes for open source compliance, and define roles and responsibilities within the company to implement them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When an open source compliance issue occurs within the company, discuss solutions and prepare countermeasures.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If necessary, report issues to the executive team to receive feedback on risk mitigation measures.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="2-open-source-program-manager">(2) Open Source Program Manager&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The open source program manager is responsible for the overall responsibility for the company&amp;rsquo;s open source programs. To ensure open source compliance of products and services using open source, open source program manager is responsible for:&lt;sub>(3.2.2.4)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Define the roles required for open source compliance, and designate a responsible person and group in charge of each role. Consult with OSRB if necessary.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Supervise and evaluate open source compliance training.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Serves as the chair of the OSRB and directs its activities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Respond to inquiries and requests related to open source use and compliance from outside.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Review and approve requests for use of open source.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Maintain open source BOM records.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Provides a way to request legal advice on open source.&lt;sub>(3.2.2.3)&lt;/sub>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Maintain a repository for open source notices and source code disclosure.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="3-ospo">(3) OSPO&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>OSPO&lt;sub>Open Source Program Office&lt;/sub> is responsible for supporting and nurturing the growth of open source activities inside and outside the company.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Establish, improve and disseminate open source policies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Provides a guide for contributing code to external open source projects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Provides a guide for releasing an in-house project as an open source.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Develop and operate an open source portal.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Develop and select open source tools.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sponsor open source project events.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Manage relationships with the open source community.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="4-legal-team">(4) Legal team&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The legal team provides advice on legal risks and mitigation measures that may arise in the process of using open source, such as interpreting open source licenses and obligations.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Advise on licensing and intellectual property issues, including conflicts due to incompatible open source licenses.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When contributing to external open source projects, review necessary legal matters such as open source licenses and CLA&lt;sub>Contributor License Agreement&lt;/sub>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="5-it-infrastructure-team">(5) IT infrastructure team&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The IT infrastructure team operates and automates open source analysis tools to build a system so that license analysis is performed automatically for supplied software.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Operate an open source license analysis tool.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Automate license analysis by integrating with DevOps.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Establish systems and processes so that license analysis is performed for supplied software.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Obtain and maintain an open source BOM for supplied software.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="6-security-officer">(6) Security Officer&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The security officer operates an open source security vulnerability analysis tool to build a system so that security vulnerability analysis is performed smoothly for supplied software.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Operate an open source security vulnerability analysis tool.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Automate open source security vulnerability analysis by integrating with DevSecOps.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Establish systems and processes so that open source security vulnerability analysis is performed for supplied software.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="7-development-culture">(7) Development Culture&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The development culture manager supports developers to actively utilize open source and participate in the open source community to learn a good development culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Encourage developers to participate in the open source community.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create a culture where activities in open source projects can be recognized as achievements.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create a development culture that can be perceived as an attractive company to open source developers.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="8-quality-responsible">(8) Quality Responsible&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The organization responsible for quality, such as QA, checks whether the open source license obligations have been properly performed when distributing software.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Check whether open source compliance activities are performed in accordance with the development process.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check that the artifacts are generated as required by the open source license.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When distributing software, make sure that the open source notice and the source code to be released are provided together.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If an issue is found, notify the software development/deployment team and guide them to fix the issue immediately.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="5-training-and-assessment">5. Training and Assessment&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>All program participants should take the open source mandatory training provided by [Learning Portal] every year. Through training, all participants should be familiar with open source policies and processes. Training history is stored in [Learning Portal].&lt;sub>(3.1.1.2)&lt;sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All members in charge of each role defined in Chapter 4 should take the advanced open source training course provided by [Learning Portal]. Training history and evaluation results are stored in [Learning Portal] for at least 3 years.&lt;sub>(3.1.2.3)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="6-use-open-source">6. Use open source&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you use open source to develop and distribute products and services, you should comply with the obligations required by each open source license. The activities that companies perform for this purpose are called open source compliance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For proper open source compliance activities, software development/distribution organizations should comply with the following:&lt;sub>(3.3.1.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>All processes of the open source compliance process are recorded and preserved in Jira Issue Tracker.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="1-identify-open-source-and-review-license-obligations">(1) Identify open source and review license obligations.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When using open source to develop products / services, first identify what an open source license is, and review and investigate the obligations that the license requires.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The company&amp;rsquo;s [Open Source License Guide] provides a guide for frequently used open source licenses, and explains the obligations for each type of distribution as follows for each license.&lt;sub>(3.3.2.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Distributed in binary form;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Distributed in source form;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Integrated with other open source such that it triggers additional licensing obligations;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Contains modified open source;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Contains open source or other software under an incompatible license interacting with other components within the supplied software; and/or&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Contains open source with attribution requirements.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Software development/distribution teams can refer to this guide when reviewing their open source license obligations. If you need to review an open source license not mentioned in this guide, contact your open source program manager.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-design-software-considering-open-source-licenses">(2) Design software considering open source licenses.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Identify open source dependencies and design your software architecture so that your code is not subject to open source licenses. .&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The company&amp;rsquo;s [Open Source Licensing Guide] describes the source code disclosure scope for each open source license and design methods to prevent disclosure of own code.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-create-an-open-source-compliance-artifact">(3) Create an open source compliance artifact.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The most basic of open source compliance activities is to identify open sources included in supplied software. This is to properly meet the open source license requirements, which are the core of open source compliance. That is, a set of compliance artifacts for open source included in the supplied software should be generated.&lt;sub>(3.4.1.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Open source compliance artifacts are divided into two main categories.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Open source notice: A document to provide full open source license and copyright notice&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Source code package to be disclosed: A package that collects source code to be disclosed to fulfill open source license obligations that require source code disclosure such as GPL, LGPL, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>To collect, distribute and store these compliance artifacts, the following should be complied with.&lt;sub>(3.4.1.2)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Open source notices or source code packages to be disclosed are collected according to the conditions required by each license. For example, a license requires the accompanying full text of the license, but not just a link.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Collected artifacts are stored in a separate storage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When providing source code to be made public by a written agreement, provide a download link so that the external general public can access the repository of the collected artifacts.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Follow the company&amp;rsquo;s open source compliance process to create and provide open source compliance artifacts as above.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-create-open-source-bill-of-materials-bom">(4) Create open source Bill of Materials (BOM)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Create and manage the Bill of Materials (BOM) included in the supplied software.&lt;sub>(3.3.1.2)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Follow the company&amp;rsquo;s open source compliance process to create and preserve open source BOMs using open source tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="5-compliance-issue-remediation-procedure">(5) Compliance Issue Remediation Procedure&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Should a non-compliance issue be raised, the Open Source Program Manager responds promptly by performing the following procedures.&lt;sub>(3.2.2.5)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Acknowledge receipt of the query and state a reasonable time for resolution;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Determine whether the query discloses a genuine issue or not (and if not, respond to the querier accordingly);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the issue is genuine, apply to prioritise, and determine the appropriate response.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Carry out response and, where necessary, improve open source compliance processes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Document the above using Jira Tracker.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="7-open-source-contributions">7. Open Source Contributions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The company encourages participation and contribution to external open source projects to create business value in open source. However, in this process, you should be careful about unintentional exposure of the company&amp;rsquo;s intellectual property or infringement of the rights of third parties. Therefore, members of the company should comply with the following when contributing to external open source projects.&lt;sub>(3.5.1.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-request-a-review-and-get-approval">(1) Request a review and get approval.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>An open source contribution is to grant an open source project the right of an author to modify/use/distribute a work from a copyright point of view. In some cases, you may need to transfer your copyright to an open source project. In general, however, the copyright of a work created during employment is owned by the employer. In other words, works created by company members are owned by the company. Contributing to open source works created while you were employed may raise unnecessary copyright infringement issues.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Therefore, if there is an open source project that you would like to contribute to, follow the review request and approval procedures before making the initial contribution according to the open source contribution process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, in the case of a small contribution as follows, since the risk of copyright infringement is not large, you can contribute at your own discretion without the review process.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Small code snippets of 10 lines or less&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Inquiries and answers on Stack Overflow&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Activities on GitHub: Issue creation, Pull Request Review / Approve, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="2-contribute-only-code-that-you-have-the-right-to-contribute">(2) Contribute only code that you have the right to contribute&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Only contribute code for which you have the right to contribute. In other words, contribute your own code, not third-party code.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-be-careful-not-to-expose-the-companys-intellectual-property">(3) Be careful not to expose the company&amp;rsquo;s intellectual property&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Do not contribute code or documents that may expose the company&amp;rsquo;s intellectual property such as sensitive information or patents.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>If the code you want to contribute includes a company&amp;rsquo;s patent, you should check whether you can contribute to the project under the open source license. If there is any ambiguity, contact OSPO.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="4-be-careful-about-signing-the-cla">(4) Be careful about signing the CLA.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Some open source projects require all contributors to sign a CLA&lt;sub>Contributor License Agreement&lt;/sub>. This is an agreement to seek consent from contributors to reduce copyright disputes that may arise when a project manages the works of multiple contributors. Typically, a company-led project requires a CLA to be signed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The CLA varies from project to project, but primarily includes agreement to the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I (or my company) have the right to contribute to the project the contribution I intend to contribute. (i.e. I am the author of this contribution.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I (or my company) grant the project the right to modify, distribute, and manage my contributions to the project.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I (or my company) will not revoke the authority granted to me.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I (or my company) grant the project the right to change the license according to future needs of the project.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In addition, in rare cases, some CLAs also require consent to the following terms and conditions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I (or my company) transfer my copyright to the project or project management organization at the same time as I contribute my contribution.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>[Company] does not allow contributions to open source projects that require transfer of copyright to protect the company&amp;rsquo;s intellectual property. Therefore, if the open source project you want to contribute to requires the CLA to be signed, be sure to ask OSPO for a review before signing.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="5-add-company-copyright-notice">(5) Add company copyright notice&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The intellectual property of the work you create during your employment is basically owned by the company. Therefore, you should add your company&amp;rsquo;s copyright notice when contributing code to external open source projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When contributing more than one file, add the copyright and license notices at the top of the files, like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>Copyright (c) {$year} {$Company}
SPDX-License-Identifier: {$SPDX_license_name}
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Here, $SPDX_license_name is written according to the license of the corresponding open source project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, if your contribution is only to modify existing code for the purpose of fixing a bug, you do not need to add a copyright notice for that code modification.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="6-use-your-company-email">(6) Use your company email&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When contributing to an open source project, use your company email, not your personal email. This will (1) give you a sense of responsibility to communicate with the community on behalf of the company, and (2) improve the awareness of the company that actively contributes to the open source community.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="8-open-source-release">8. Open Source Release&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[Company] respects the value of collaboration with the open source community and encourages the release of internal software as an open source project. However, there are several rules that should be followed to protect the company&amp;rsquo;s intellectual property and prevent unintentional copyright infringement.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-get-approval">(1) Get approval&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>From a copyright point of view, releasing as open source means that the author grants the right to modify/use/distribute the work by anyone through an open source license. In general, the copyright of a work created during employment is owned by the employer. In other words, the work you create is owned by the company. The act of arbitrarily releasing a work as open source may cause unnecessary copyright infringement issues.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Therefore, if you want to release the software as open source, follow the review request and approval procedure according to the company&amp;rsquo;s open source release policy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Do not hesitate to contact OSPO if anything in your open source process appears to be undesirable.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-release-only-the-code-you-have-the-right-to-publish">(2) Release only the code you have the right to publish.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One of the worst things that can happen to an open source project is that the project contains legally problematic code. Code that the company does not have the right to release, or code that infringes IP, such as another company&amp;rsquo;s patent, can cause legal problems. Therefore, while preparing the code to be released, check the source of all code and delete problematic code.‌&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-be-careful-about-the-exposure-of-the-companys-intellectual-property">(3) Be careful about the exposure of the company&amp;rsquo;s intellectual property.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Do not release code or documents that may expose sensitive information or patents to the company&amp;rsquo;s intellectual property.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the code you want to release contains a company patent, see if you can release it under the open source license. If there are any ambiguities, please contact OSPO.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-publish-useful-code">(4) Publish useful code&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>To be a successful project, it should also be useful to others. If a similar project already exists, join the existing project rather than create a new one.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An open source that intends to release should be able to expect: (1) provide differentiated value to the open source community; (2) to solve problems that the community has not been able to solve; (3) We receive positive attention by releasing our technology.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>If the code we haven&amp;rsquo;t used in our products or services, don&amp;rsquo;t even release it as open source.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do not publish code that addresses a problem that has already been addressed by the open source community. If this is the case, contribute to an existing open source project.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="5-prepare-the-resource">(5) Prepare the resource&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Prepare in advance the resources that will be put into the open source project, including developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In the beginning, the number of developers similar to that of a general in-house project is required.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Get developers who can quickly review external contributions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The role of the legal team and marketing team is also required.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Secure a budget for the infrastructure required to maintain and manage the project. This includes tools for hosting projects like Github.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>If you can&amp;rsquo;t create an environment with enough resources to support it, don&amp;rsquo;t release it as open source.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="6-use-your-company-email-1">(6) Use your company email&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For open source release activities, do not use personal emails, but use company emails. This will (1) give you a sense of responsibility to communicate with the community on behalf of the company, and (2) improve the awareness of the company that actively contributes to the open source community.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="9-respond-to-external-inquiries">9. Respond to external inquiries&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="1-responsibility-for-responding-to-external-inquiries">(1) Responsibility for responding to external inquiries&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The open source program manager is responsible for responding to inquiries and requests for open source compliance from outside.&lt;sub>(3.2.1.2)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The open source program manager may assign all or part of the handling of inquiries to appropriate personnel within the company. If necessary, contact the legal team to deal with it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Anyone who receives an inquiry about open source compliance from outside will notify the open source program manager so that a prompt response can be made.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="2-disclosure-of-contact-information">(2) Disclosure of contact information&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The open source program manager publicly provides the contact information of the person in charge so that external inquiries and requests related to open source can be submitted to the company.&lt;sub>(3.2.1.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Include the email address of the person in charge in the open source notice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Register your contact in the Linux Foundation&amp;rsquo;s Open Compliance Directory.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="3-external-inquiry-response-procedure">(3) External Inquiry Response Procedure&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>If you respond quickly and accurately to open source compliance inquiries from outside, you can significantly reduce the risk of going to a lawsuit. To this end, in order to respond to external open source compliance inquiries, you should follow the external inquiry response process defined in the company&amp;rsquo;s open source compliance process.&lt;sub>(3.2.1.2)&lt;/sub>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="10-openchain">10. OpenChain&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>회사는 소프트웨어 공급망에서의 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 수준 향상을 위해 Linux Foundation의 OpenChain 프로젝트의 정신을 지지하며 적극적으로 참여한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>회사는 이 오픈소스 정책을 적용하여 2021년 10월 1일부로 ISO/IEC 5230:2020을 준수함을 보장한다.&lt;sub>(3.6.1.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>회사는 적합성 인증을 획득한 후 18개월 이상 OpenChain 규격 버전 2.1, ISO/IED 5230:2020의 모든 요구사항을 충족함을 보장한다.&lt;sub>(3.6.2.1)&lt;/sub>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>회사는 최소 18개월 간격으로 적합성을 검토하고 필요에 따라 정책을 변경 및 갱신한다.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="appendix-1-list-of-persons-in-charge">Appendix 1. List of persons in charge&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>No&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">role&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">responsibility&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Required Competencies&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Responsible Organization&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Contact Person&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>1&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Open Source Program Manager&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">This role is responsible for general responsibility for the company&amp;rsquo;s open source programs.&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">1. Understanding the software development process&lt;br>2. Understanding intellectual property related to open source licenses such as copyrights and patents&lt;br>3. Expertise in Open Source Compliance&lt;br>4. Open source development experience&lt;br>5. Communication Skills&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">CTO&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">OOO&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>2&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Legal&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Interpret open source licenses and obligations. This role provides advice on the mitigation of legal risks that may arise for the use of open source, such as the actual implementation of these obligations.&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">1. Basic knowledge of open source ecosystem&lt;br>2. Expertise in software copyright&lt;br>3. Expertise in Open Source Licensing&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Legal Team&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">OOO&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>3&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Infrastructure&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">This role operates and automates open source analysis tools to build systems so that license analysis is performed automatically for all supplied software.&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">1. Basic knowledge of open source compliance process&lt;br>2. Understanding of open source license analysis tools&lt;br>3. IT infrastructure expertise&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">IT Infrastructure Team&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">OOO&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>4&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Security&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">This role operates an open source security vulnerability analysis tool to build a system so that security vulnerability analysis is automatically performed for all supplied software.&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">1. Basic knowledge of open source compliance process&lt;br>2. Understanding of open source license analysis tools&lt;br>3. Security Expertise&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Security Team&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">OOO&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>5&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Development culture&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">This role supports developers to actively utilize open source and learn a good development culture by participating in the open source community.&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">1. Understanding the software development process&lt;br>2. Basic knowledge of open source compliance&lt;br>3. Understanding Open Source Policies&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">DR&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">OOO&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>6&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">development team&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">In this role, software development/distribution organizations adhere to open source policies and processes for proper use of open source.&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">1. Understanding the software development process&lt;br>2. Basic knowledge of open source compliance&lt;br>3. Understanding of Open Source Policy&lt;br>4. Basic knowledge of open source licenses&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Development team&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">All developers&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>Guide: 2. 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 프로세스 (샘플)</title><link>https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/2-process/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/2-process/</guid><description>
&lt;p>OOO 주식회사(이하 &amp;ldquo;회사&amp;quot;라 함)는 소프트웨어를 포함하는 제품과 서비스를 개발하면서 오픈소스 소프트웨어(이하 &amp;ldquo;오픈소스&amp;quot;라 함)를 적극적으로 활용한다. 회사는 소프트웨어를 배포하면서 오픈소스 라이선스가 부과하는 의무사항을 준수하기 위한 활동을 수행해야 하며 이를 오픈소스 컴플라이언스라고 한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="1-소프트웨어-제품-개발배포를-위한-프로세스">1. 소프트웨어 제품 개발/배포를 위한 프로세스&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>오픈소스 컴플라이언스 프로세스는 회사가 소프트웨어 제품 및 서비스를 개발하고 배포하기 위한 각 개발 단계에 맞게 오픈소스 라이선스 의무 준수를 위해 수행해야 할 절차를 정의한다. 소프트웨어 제품 개발/배포에 관여하는 모든 구성원은 다음의 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 프로세스 10단계를 준수한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="general-osc-process.png" alt="general-osc-process">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-오픈소스-식별subidentification-of-open-sourcesub">1. 오픈소스 식별&lt;sub>Identification of Open Source&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 소프트웨어 설계 단계에서 다음 사항을 준수한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>소프트웨어를 설계하면서 예측 가능한 오픈소스 사용 현황을 파악하고 라이선스를 확인한다.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>오픈소스 라이선스별 의무 사항을 확인한다. 라이선스별 의무 사항은 회사의 오픈소스 라이선스 가이드에서 확인할 수 있다.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>각 오픈소스 라이선스의 소스 코드 공개 범위를 고려하여 소프트웨어를 설계한다.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 주요 오픈소스 라이선스 의무, 제한, 권리에 대한 가이드를 작성하고 공개하여 전사의 개발 부서에서 참고하게 한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 회사 규칙에 맞게 소스 코드에 저작권 및 라이선스를 표기한다. 회사의 소스 코드 내 저작권 및 라이선스 표기 규칙은 다음 페이지에서 확인할 수 있다. : (insert_link)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 새로운 오픈소스 도입 검토 시, 먼저 라이선스를 식별한다. 회사의 오픈소스 라이선스 가이드에 따라 라이선스 의무, 제한 및 권리를 확인한다. 회사의 오픈소스 라이선스 가이드에서 설명하지 않는 라이선스일 경우, 오픈소스 프로그램 매니저에게 도입 가능 여부 및 주의 사항을 문의한다. Jira Ticket을 생성하여 문의한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 오픈소스 라이선스 의무를 분석하여 소프트웨어 개발 조직에 안내한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>의문이 있는 경우, 법무 담당에 자문을 요청하여 명확한 가이드를 제공한다.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>새롭게 분석한 라이선스 정보는 전사 라이선스 가이드에 반영한다.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="2-소스-코드-검사subauditing-source-codesub">2. 소스 코드 검사&lt;sub>Auditing Source Code&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 인프라 담당의 안내에 따라 소스 코드를 제공하여 오픈소스 점검을 요청한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>인프라 담당은 오픈소스 분석 도구를 사용하여 오픈소스 점검을 하고, 오픈소스 BOM을 생성한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 오픈소스 라이선스 의무 준수 가능 여부, 오픈소스 라이선스 충돌 여부를 검토하고, 이슈가 있으면, 개발 부서에 해결을 요청한다. 이슈 사항은 Jira Ticket으로 생성하여 개발 부서에 할당한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-문제-해결subresolving-issuessub">3. 문제 해결&lt;sub>Resolving Issues&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 소스 코드 검사 단계에서 발견된 모든 문제를 해결한다. 이슈가 된 오픈소스를 제거하거나, 다른 라이선스 하의 오픈소스로 교체하는 등 조치를 한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 발견된 모든 이슈를 해결하면 Jira Ticket 이슈를 Resolve하고, 재검토를 요청한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-검토subreviewssub">4. 검토&lt;sub>Reviews&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 모든 이슈가 적절하게 보완되었는지를 검토한다. 필요할 경우, 오픈소스 분석 도구를 사용하여 소스 코드 검사를 재수행한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="5-승인subapprovalsub">5. 승인&lt;sub>Approval&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 절차가 적절하게 수행되었는지를 최종 승인 혹은 거절한다. 거절 시에는 이유에 대한 설명과 수정 방법을 개발 부서에 제안한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="6-등록subregistrationsub">6. 등록&lt;sub>Registration&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 소프트웨어의 버전별 오픈소스 사용 목록을 추적하기 위한 BOM을 확정한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>인프라 담당은 확정된 BOM을 시스템에 등록한다. BOM에는 배포용 소프트웨어에 포함된 오픈소스 목록과 다음과 같은 정보를 포함한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>배포용 소프트웨어의 제품(혹은 서비스) 이름과 버전&lt;/li>
&lt;li>오픈소스 목록
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>오픈소스 이름 / 버전&lt;/li>
&lt;li>오픈소스 라이선스&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="7-고지subnoticessub">7. 고지&lt;sub>Notices&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 고지 의무를 준수하기 위한 오픈소스 고지문을 생성한다. 오픈소스 고지문에는 다음 사항을 포함한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>오픈소스 관련 문의할 수 있는 오픈소스 연락처&lt;/li>
&lt;li>오픈소스별 고지 내용
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>저작권&lt;/li>
&lt;li>오픈소스 라이선스 이름&lt;/li>
&lt;li>오픈소스 라이선스 사본&lt;/li>
&lt;li>(해당하는 경우) 소스 코드 사본을 얻을 수 있는 서면 약정 (Written Offer)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 오픈소스 고지문을 생성하여 개발 부서에 전달한다. 이때 소스 코드 공개가 필요할 경우 개발 부서에 공개할 소스 코드 취합 방법을 안내한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 오픈소스 고지문을 제품 배포 시 동봉한다. 화면이 있는 제품일 경우, 사용자가 메뉴를 통해 확인할 수 있도록 조치한다. (예: 앱 &amp;gt; 메뉴 &amp;gt; 설정 &amp;gt; 저작권 정보 &amp;gt; 오픈소스 라이선스)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 GPL, LGPL 등 소스 코드 공개를 요구하는 라이선스 하의 오픈소스를 사용하였을 경우, 이에 대한 소스 코드 공개 범위를 확인하여 공개할 소스 코드를 취합한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>GPL, LGPL 등의 라이선스 의무 준수를 위해 취합한 소스 코드는 제품에 탑재된 바이너리를 구성하는 소스 코드와 일치해야 한다. 즉, 취합한 소스 코드를 빌드하면 제품에 탑재된 바이너리와 동일해야 한다.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="8-배포-전-확인subpre-distribution-verificationssub">8. 배포 전 확인&lt;sub>Pre-Distribution Verifications&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>개발 부서는 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 활동이 적절히 수행되었음을 입증하는 다음의 산출물을 제출한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>제품에 포함한 최종 오픈소스 고지문&lt;/li>
&lt;li>제품에 오픈소스 고지문이 포함되었음을 확인하는 자료 (예: 오픈소스 고지문을 보여주는 화면 캡처 이미지)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>(해당할 경우) 공개할 소스 코드 (하나의 파일로 압축하여 제출)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 개발 부서가 제출한 자료를 검토하여 이상 여부를 확인한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="9-배포subdistributionsub">9. 배포&lt;sub>Distribution&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 개발 부서가 제출한 컴플라이언스 산출물을 인프라 담당에 제출한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>인프라 담당은 컴플라이언스 산출물을 회사의 오픈소스 배포 사이트에 등록한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="10-최종-확인-final-verifications">10. 최종 확인 (Final Verifications)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 컴플라이언스 산출물이 이상 없이 회사의 오픈소스 포털에 등록이 되었는지, 외부에서 이상 없이 다운로드가 되는지 등 종합적인 확인을 한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="2-외부-문의-대응-프로세스">2. 외부 문의 대응 프로세스&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>외부로부터의 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 문의에 신속하고 정확하게 대응한다면 소송까지 진행되는 위험을 크게 줄일 수 있다. 이를 위해 기업은 외부의 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 문의에 대응하기 위해 다음과 같은 프로세스를 준수한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="general-inquiry-process.png" alt="general-inquiry-process">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-접수-알림subacknowledgesub">1. 접수 알림&lt;sub>Acknowledge&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 문의를 받은 즉시 요청자에게 문의가 접수되었음을 알린다. 이때 조치 예정일을 함께 알린다. 요청자의 의도가 무엇인지 정확히 파악하는 것이 중요하기 때문에 문의가 불명확한 경우 추가 설명을 요청한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>대응이 필요한 문의 및 요청의 주요 내용은 아래와 같다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>특정 제품 및 서비스에 오픈소스가 사용되었는지 문의&lt;/li>
&lt;li>서면 약정(Written Offer)에 언급된 GPL, LGPL 라이선스 하의 소스 코드 제공 요청&lt;/li>
&lt;li>오픈소스 고지문에 명시되지 않았지만, 제품에서 발견된 오픈소스에 대한 해명 및 소스 코드 공개 요청&lt;/li>
&lt;li>GPL, LGPL 등의 의무로 공개된 소스 코드에 누락된 파일 및 빌드 방법 제공 요청&lt;/li>
&lt;li>저작권 표시 요청&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 접수한 요청에 대한 Jira Issue를 생성하여 대응 상황을 모두 자세히 기록한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-조사-알림subinformsub">2. 조사 알림&lt;sub>Inform&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 요청자에게 오픈소스 컴플라이언스를 충실히 수행하고 있음과 요청자의 문의를 조사하고 있음을 알린다. 내부 조사 진행 상황이 업데이트될 때마다 알리는 것이 좋다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-내부-조사subinvestigatesub">3. 내부 조사&lt;sub>Investigate&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 요청 사항에 대한 내부 조사를 진행한다. 문제가 된 제품의 버전에 대하여 컴플라이언스 프로세스가 적절하게 수행되었는지 BOM 및 문서화된 검토 이력을 통해 확인한다. 필요 시 법무 담당에 자문을 요청한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>특정 개발 부서에서 확인이 필요한 사항일 경우 오픈소스 프로그램 매니저는 개발 부서에 조사를 요청한다. 조사를 요청받은 개발 부서는 컴플라이언스 산출물에 문제가 있는지 즉시 확인하고 결과를 오픈소스 프로그램 매니저에게 보고한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-요청자에게-보고subreportsub">4. 요청자에게 보고&lt;sub>Report&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>요픈소스 컴플라이언스 담당은 조치 예정일 내에 내부 조사를 마치고, 요청자에게 결과를 알린다.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>요청자의 문의가 오해로 인한 잘못된 지적이었다면 추가 조치 없이 요청자에게 이를 알리고 처리를 종료한다.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>문제가 맞는다면 요청자에게 해당 오픈소스 라이선스의 의무를 이행하기 위한 정확한 방법과 시기를 알린다.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="5-문제-보완--알림subrectifysub">5. 문제 보완 / 알림&lt;sub>Rectify&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>내부조사에서 실제 컴플라이언스 문제가 발견되면 해당 개발 부서는 컴플라이언스 문제를 해결하는 데 필요한 모든 절차를 수행한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="6-문제-해결-알림subreportsub">6. 문제 해결 알림&lt;sub>Report&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>문제를 해결한 후에는 즉시 요청자에게 알리고 문제가 해결되었음을 확인할 수 있는 최선의 방법을 제공한다.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="7-프로세스-개선subimprovesub">7. 프로세스 개선&lt;sub>Improve&lt;/sub>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>컴플라이언스 문제가 있었던 경우, OSRB 미팅을 통해 사례를 검토하고, 문제가 발생한 경위를 파악하여, 문제가 재발하지 않을 수 있도록 프로세스를 개선한다.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Guide: 3. Tools (FOSSology, SW360)</title><link>https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/3-tools/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://openChain-project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/guide/governance_iso5230/appendix/3-tools/</guid><description>
&lt;p>오픈소스 컴플라이언스 활동을 위해서는 정책, 프로세스나 교육자료뿐만 아니라 소스코드 스캔, Dependency 분석, 오픈소스 BOM 관리 등을 위한 다양한 도구와 시스템도 요구된다. 때문에 다수의 기업이 이러한 도구와 시스템을 도입하고 활용하는 데 많은 리소스를 투입하고 있다. 특히 오픈소스 컴플라이언스를 처음 시작하는 기업은 프로세스뿐 아니라 비용 측면에서도 어려움을 겪고 있다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>이런 어려움을 해결하기 위해, 2019년 6월, OpenChain 프로젝트에 참여하고 있는 지멘스, 보쉬, 도시바, 후지쓰, 히타치 등의 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 도구 전문가들을 주축으로 OpenChain Tooling Work Group이 시작되었다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>OpenChain Tooling Work Group은 여러 기업의 오픈소스 전문가들이 이슈를 함께 해결하고 결과물을 공유해 오픈소스 컴플라이언스 비용을 절감하고 양질의 컴플라이언스 결과물을 만들어 내기 위해 구성되었다.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>구체적으로는 FOSSology, SW360, Software Heritage, ClearlyDefined, SPDX 등의 기존 오픈소스 프로젝트를 활용하여 통합(turn-key) 오픈소스 툴 체인을 만들고, 모든 기업이 이를 자유롭게 사용할 수 있도록 하는 것을 목표로 삼고 있다. (&lt;a href="https://groups.io/g/oss-based-compliance-tooling">https://groups.io/g/oss-based-compliance-tooling&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>여기서는 FOSSology와 SW360에 대해 소개 및 간단한 사용 방법에 대해 알아본다.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>