<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OpenChain KWG News in 2020 on OpenChain KWG</title><link>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/</link><description>Recent content in OpenChain KWG News in 2020 on OpenChain KWG</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>ISO Standard, OpenChain</title><link>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/12/16/iso-standard-openchain/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/12/16/iso-standard-openchain/</guid><description>On December 15, 2020, OpenChain Specification 2.1 was officially published as an international standard ISO/IEC 5230:2020.
For more information on this, please refer to the following article. : https://world.einnews.com/pr_news/532725924/iso-iec-5230-2020-is-the-international-standard-for-open-source-compliance</description></item><item><title>Kakao Training Material</title><link>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/11/24/kakao-training-material/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/11/24/kakao-training-material/</guid><description>The open source technology part of Kakao has released open source educational materials for in-house developers so that anyone can read it.
Download Training materials can be downloaded from the following page.
http://t1.kakaocdn.net/olive/assets/opensource_guide_kakao.pdf</description></item><item><title>NCSOFT Training Material</title><link>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/11/23/ncsoft-training-material/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/11/23/ncsoft-training-material/</guid><description>NCSOFT has released lecture slides and scripts, which are open source educational materials in-house, on GitHub based on the spirit of sharing open source so that anyone can use them.
Companies that develop/distribute software can use this slide as it is or extract/modify necessary parts when preparing for in-house open source training.
Anyone can participate in modifying and supplementing these materials through GitHub.
Download These materials can be downloaded from the following page.</description></item><item><title>Open Source Compliance in the Enterprise</title><link>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/11/23/open-source-compliance-in-the-enterprise/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://OpenChain-Project.github.io/OpenChain-KWG/en/blog/2020/11/23/open-source-compliance-in-the-enterprise/</guid><description>Introducing the Open Source Compliance in the Enterprise book This book was written by Ibrahim Haddad and published by the Linux Foundation.
It explains in detail what to consider when building an open source compliance program in a business, and anyone can download it from the following link : Download
Korean summary NCSOFT summarized the main contents of this book in Korean, and after getting permission from the author, Ibrahim, they released it so that open source people of Korean companies can refer to it.</description></item></channel></rss>